In a church in southern Småland
is our play painted on the wall
to the left when you enter the building.
The painting originates in the
late 14th century
and the subject was formed by the plague
that visited this landscape.
The artist is
unknown.
I have therefore called the play
Wooden Painting
and follows the painting's story
which starts in the weapon house's
small windows
where the sun shines over a
still-green landscape
and ends four meters further in
a dark corner
where the final events happen
in a rainy, gray dawn.
Nobody may pass further inside
As you can't recognise us,
I forgive you
I can't help it,
but it's forbidden to cross the threshold
And why doesn't your father, brother or
husband tell us that it's forbidden?
My brother's ill.
My father hasn't returned from the war.
My husband died three days ago.
I'll have a word with your brother.  He
will recognise both me and my master.
No, don't.
I understand your worry
Just because we look dirty and soiled
that doesn't make us villains.
We've got the plague.
Oops, that's not good.
That's disgusting.
Oops.
Nobody escapes.
There's no cure.
No escape.
Do you smell the smoke?
It's been over the woods since this morning.
When you mention it, I do feel something
stinging my nose.
They burned a witch at the crossroads
this morning.
It's considered that she's the cause of
the plague.
By the way, she did admit to having
sexual congress with...  the dark one.
But dear, then everything well and good!
You have to keep up with those damned
witches, whether they conjure up plague...
... or whatever devilish thing they're doing.
My master wants us to continue.
What is your master's name?
His name is Antonius Block, and he's
your master as much as mine.
For ten years we sat down in the holy
land, letting snakes bite us...
... animals gnaw at us, heathens light
us on fire...
... wine poison us, women giving us lice...
... fleas eat is up, and fevers burn us up.
For God's honour!
Now you're throwing twigs at me, my lord...
... but I was right.  Our crusade was so
stupid that only an idealist could have
thought of it.
Just look at my master.  He can't talk.
The dirty heathens captured him one
Sunday morning during services.
And they cut his tongue out of his mouth.
Thanks to me...
... the plague...
... more insulting than what we've experienced.
I don't give a damn about the plague.
Goodbye, my girl.
Even if I lack funds for your information
you'll have to keep an account until we
meet in heaven.
If you get there, that is.
They should obey.
They haven't seen their infected eyes,
their hands
the blood that foams around their eyes
and mouths.
They haven't seen the boils on their necks.
Every morning it's bigger than in the
evening.
And water and pus runs from it.
On some it grows as big as a
child's head, and their bodies...
... and their bodies shrink so their
limbs become ropes of madness.
They try to tear the boils off.
They bit their hands.
They tear their veins open with their
nails.
Their screams tear the clouds.
Then they dance over the floor.
Then they fall, and then they gasp
And then they die.
In the trenches.
In the barns.
On the farms.
In the river.
In the stoves.
The people flee the cities.
They go north
and the entire time a shadow follows them.
A stricter master.
New areas are hit.
It's the end times.
In the sunset it's as if you can see the
horsemen.
The wild riders of the apocalypse.
Poor little Jens.
How dark the forest is.
Even if the sun has barely set.
A huge crab sits under my ribs and grabs
at my heart.
Perhaps I should try singing a little song.
In the ocean the fishes swim
Big ships are rocked.
Sensible people die like flies.
Are you afraid, Jens?
Uh-uh.
Are you afraid, little Jens?
No...
Aren't you at all afraid, my poor little
Jens?
Yes!
I am so scared that an accident could
happen at any time.
But my stomach is as empty as infinity.
But who are you, my beautiful girl?
Aren't you afraid of the dark?
Can I join you?
My master and I are just resting.
You see, we've just strolled from the
holy country.
- So we're a bit tired, you see.
- OK, then I'll... rest, too.
Follow me into the bushes over there.
Why should I do that?
Perhaps we could pick some blueberries,
for instance?
- It's been so long.
- If you knew who I am...
... you wouldn't suggest picking
blueberries.
Or anything else, for that matter.
- Who are you then, if I may ask?
- I'm the witch!
That they burned over at the crossroads
this morning.
Then you really shouldn't be standing
here, being dead and all.
Of course I'm dead!
Oh!  Then you're a ghost?
And I don't believe in ghosts, which
means that you don't exist.
Which means that you can't be standing
there bothering me.
Unless we're dead too, and transformed
into ghosts.  If that's the case,
then I don't give a damn, so don't say
another word until the end of days.
Perhaps you and your master participated
in the execution?
No, unfortunately!  We've just been abroad.
Near the morning, I fell asleep for a
while.
But I awoke almost immediately by the
crowd hissing outside the prison.  I was
afraid, and I cried.
But that didn't help.  Everything had
already been decided.
I climbed up to the little window and
looked down on the yard.
The wagon they were going to drive me
away in was there.
The priest had also arrived.
But I couldn't see whether the
executioner was there.
The sun was rising.
There wasn't a cloud in the skies.
It was completely empty.
I stood there, looking at the people.
And I was able to distinguish their
faces.
And their voices entered my ears.
And they were like evil birds.
And then I looked at my hands, holding
on to the protrusion on the wall.
The nails were black with blood, and
broken.
But my knuckles whitened, and all my
strength remained!
Then voices could be heard in the hall.
The door was opened, and I fell down
from the wall.
I lay with my forehead on the rough
planks that stank of rotten straw.
They bent down, took me across the
waist, and they pulled my shoulders
and they placed an iron claw over
my neck.
And I was cold.
So cold I couldn't speak.
Couldn't scream.
Couldn't walk.
But they pulled on my collar.
They pulled me down the stone steps and
through a long hall, and every time I
fell, I almost choked.
Then they pulled on the chain.
But they didn't touch my body.
Like the other guards.
They didn't laugh and make fun of me
like those who cut my hair.  No, they
were silent and worried.
They pulled my collar and they were
afraid.
Because they knew that He accompanied me
and hold onto my dress.
Then the doors opened and the sun struck
my face.
And there was like an outcry in the sun.
And the morning wind tore up sand
and threw it in our faces.
I sat in the wagon.
Back to front.
Tethered, so that I had to hold my head
safely against my chest.
And when the wagon shook along the road,
it hurt.
Because the iron cut into my throat.
But I didn't scream.
The pain helped me.
The rocks on the road helped me.
The creaking wheels helped me.
There was nothing in front and nothing
behind me.
And the sun burned in red waves through
my eyelids
and I heard the stamping of hundreds of
feet.
The road dust rose like smoke.
I felt how the people around me
breathed, and how their pulses beat.
And their eyes widened.
But they were all silent.
When we reached the place by
the crossroads
they loosened my tether.
And I bent my head backwards.
Over the pines
above everything
there were streams of thin clouds.
Like hands.
Then I smelled the smoke!
It was coming from a huge heap of
twigs and everybody started coughing.
The flames rose.  It was a huge fire.
It heated our faces
and I turned away.
And behind me, He stood.
And his mouth curved upwards.
And his eyes became round and clear.
He came close to me.
I felt his breath against my cheek.
And He put His hand on my thigh.
I turned towards the heap.
And all the people who were hiding
behind it.
I stretched my fingers out.  I stood on
my toes.
I stretched as far as I could.
And then I laughed!  I laughed...
But it sounds like when a small
child laughs.
So I started screaming.
Words appeared in my scream.
They were like fishes in a lake.
Now the wheel is turning.  Now the sand
is raging.
Now the night bird is screaming.
Now everything collides.
The viper.
Now the wheel has stopped.
Now the holy rites are rising.
Now the wheel stands still.
Now there's silence.
Now the leap is close.
Now the sand has its own.
Now the mountains are roaring.
Now the river is gaping.
Now they're here.
Then they struck me across the mouth
with a cane so I fell down.
Then they tied me to a ladder.
And put it into the fire.
And the flames flew up.
Enveloped my clothes.
And before I fell into the pyre with my
face first
I burned like a torch.
They sang a psalm.
But I was no longer scared.
He held his furry body in front of
mine.
And we fell
into a deep lake.
He enveloped me
and I wasn't cold any more.
Sorry for disturbing.
Have any of you seen my wife?
No, we haven't seen even a cat.
That's too bad.
Has she disappeared?
She'd gone off with a jester.
If she's got that bad taste, I think you
should just let her run off.
Don't do her the honour of running
around the woods looking for her.
That's not it, my lord.
I had rather thought I was going to kill
her.
Oh, I see.  Well, that's a different
thing altogether.
I'm going to kill the cheating jester,
too.
There's too many of those, anyway.  Even
if they haven't done anything, they
should be killed.
You see, my wife has always been so
interested in...  the art of theatre.
And that was her misfortune.
Her misfortune, but not mine.
Because one that's born as a mistake
can't be affected by misfortune.
Of what kind is self-evident.
Are you married, by any chance?
A hundred times and more.  I can't even
count my wives any more.
But it's often that way when you're
travelling.
One wife is worse than a hundred, I tell
you.
Or perhaps I've been struck worse than
most
poor sods in this miserable world.
Which doesn't seem unlikely to me.
It's hell with women, and it's hell
without women.
No matter how you think about it, it's
always makes most sense to
just kill them while it's still fun.
Women's whining
children's cries and pee-filled diapers
sharp tacks and jeers
hits and slaps and horrible
mother-in-laws
and when you're going to bed after a
long day, the pipe gets another tune:
Tears, whining, complaints:
"Why don't you kiss me goodnight?
why don't you sing a song?
Why don't you love me like when we
first met?
Why haven't you looked at my new robe?
You just lie there and snore?"
Oh, yes.
And then that...  jester arrived.
With his stench of perfume.
He was so full of false smiles.
And played.  Played on his goddamned
stringed instrument.
And sighted and wept, with blue eyes and
rosy cheeks.
And swanned around with his ass in the
air like a cat.
While my mother-in-law stood guard
while I was made a cuckold.
- And then they sneaked off.
I'm going to pinch them with my pliers...
I'll pound them on their chests with
my hammer.
I'll tap them ever so lightly on their
heads with my big sledge.
What on Earth...
Are you crying?
Yes, look at the smith...
He whines and he cries like a
piss-soaked rabbit.
Now I'm confused.
You're free from that rascal!
You don't understand me.
Your vanity is hurt.
That's something one can endure.
Then you're not a real man.
Perhaps he loves her?
Hah!  A ghost talks!
"Perhaps he loves her!"
Listen here, you deep fried sorceress,
what do you know about love!
What do you know about love?
Everything that's worth knowing, and a
great deal besides.
It's another word for lust, plus lust,
plus lust...
plus a whole deal of fraud, falsehoods,
lies
and common swindles.
Love is the blackest of all plagues
and if you died of it, then perhaps
there'd be some point
but it almost always passes.  Only some
sheep brains die from it from time to
time.
Love is as contagious as the common cold
it steals your blood, your power, your
independence
your morals (if you have any).
Love is an exhausting grimace that ends
with a yawn.
If everything in this world is
imperfect, then love is most perfect in
its perfect imperfection.
Damn, all this talking makes my throat
dry.  Do you have any liquor?
You're a lucky guy, with a mouth on you
like that.
And you even believe in your own
nonsense.
But beware: The forest is dark and night
is coming.
Beware what you're saying!
This is my gospel:
My small stomach is my Earth
my head is my eternity
and my hands is my sons.
The legs are time's unholy pendulums.
And my dirty feet are two marvellous
starting points for my philosophy.
My world in the Jens World, credible for
nobody except myself.
Ridiculous for everybody, even myself.
Meaningless before heaven and
indifferent in hell.
Everything is worth exactly as much as a
yawn
only with the difference that a yawn is
more pleasurable.
Oh, oh, oh, now I remembered...
What are you whining about?
Oh, I was thinking about my wife, you
see...
She's so beautiful.
She's so beautiful you can't
describe her
without accompaniment of a lute.
And that's exactly what the jester did.
Her smile is like liquor.
Her eyes like blueberries.
Her behind is like a juicy pear.
That woman is like a strawberry field.
I can picture her now...
with arms like lovely cucumbers.
Yuck!  Stop!  You're a really bad poet,
despite being drunk.
And your vegetables bore me.
Can I come along with you part of
the way?
OK, but if you start crying again, I'm
leaving you behind.
Oh, is the witch joining us?
What a group of people...
The moon is rising.
- Then we'll see the way better.
- I don't like the moon.
The trees are so still tonight.
That's because there's no wind.
What I mean is that they're very still.
Bats.  They're always flying over the
road and in front of our faces.
It's totally quiet.
A dog's bark?
A human voice?
The moonlight is burning the eyes so
that one can hardly see.
It's dangerous to stand in the
moonlight, don't you know what?
Does anybody know the right way to the
border?  These are just narrow paths,
and I'm lost.
If you come along with us, you'll
find plague.
If you turn the opposite way, you'll
That is, if plague doesn't find you
long before.
But it's the plague I'm afraid of.
I took my little boy out of the cradle
and I've walked all day without
meeting anybody.
Does anybody have some bread?
Here's a piece of my last loaf.  If
you're able to chew it, you're better
than me.
But I've only got two teeth, of course.
Shut up!
The time has come!
What is that among the trees if not my
most honoured, with accompanying jester.
Be my guests; please have a seat.
Because now there's going to be a
trial.
My wife!
I see that you're having a little
evening nap!
With a lap dog!
Or whatever it is that's swishing at
your left side.
Are you the filthy smith that's
insulting my beloved lady?
My most beloved Kunnigunnan?
Kunni-
Lisa! Is her name.
Or slut!
Lisa Faithless!
Ass-Lisa!
You're good at filth; you think
something up.
You little gilded miscreant.
You cropped bastard offspring of seven
scabrous mongrels:
If I were in your flea-ridden pants,
shame would have struck me down
over my bad breath, my way of moving,
my voice; in short, my entire person
that I would immediately liberate nature
from my awful visage.
Uh-uh.
I'm going to smash your mouth in.
You won't even be able to perform your
tricks for cannibals.
Heathens!
Bravo!
Huh?
Now I'm going to kick you in the stomach
so your entrails are going to spurt out
your ears!
Not as good.
Look at me, gentlemen, poor
despondent woman.
And then listen to these men.
- Look at the actor.  Listen closely to
his voice.
- My voice?
Oh, right.  My voice.
My talent.
Yes, imagine.  You've got a voice.
You even have some corns!
You can't claim to be a human person.
He's a fraud?
I suggest that we end this argument.
Do you drink the smith's liquor and kill
the actor?
Please understand me, gentlemen.
When he whispered his screeds in my ears
I didn't know they were lines from
his repertoire.
When he landed me the first time, I
didn't know that that scene had
been rehearsed.
In front of a theatre's director, or in
front of a dusty mirror.
When his beard tickled me in a
strange way
I didn't know that it was a false beard
And his smile...  a collection
of fake teeth that grow
progressively worse the further you get
into his mouth.
He's stolen his perfumes, he's filched
his songs
and he's taken his gestures from
somebody else.
But, my gentleman, is it correct to say
that an actor is a living human being
like the rest of us?
Well, let's see if he bleeds.
My ladies and gentlemen.
If you think I'm going to give some sort
of defence speech
for my so-called reality, you're
gravely mistaken.
I'm an actor without a theatre.
A straw doll without a doll house.  A
poet without poetry.
A lover without love.
Even fleas shy away from me.
Very well, my lord, I throw away my
wooden sword.
I will not defend myself.
You have to fight me.  Otherwise I can't
kill you.
At least, you have to make me as angry
as I was just now.
I take my dagger and place it against
my heart.
Just give it a push, and my irreality
will soon change into
a solid and indisputable reality:
The corpse's absolute tangibility.
Do something!
Don't just stand there.
He's a disgrace both for himself and
for you.
End this misery, he's asking for it.
Well, if you don't dare, then I'll
do it.
Ouch ouch help
I'm dyyyying
I'm dyying
And that's somebody I have to be
married to?
Come along.  This is nothing to
reflect on.
Let us break camp.
I feel ill at easy.
Perhaps one has eaten something off.
One hasn't eaten anything at all!
Look at the knight.
He stands there looking at the juggler,
and then he suddenly laughs.
I don't see anything funny about a
dead jester.
Not a living one, either.
Have they left?
Yes, they've left.
Then I can get up.
Where's my dagger?
Oh, right.
I'm ashamed...  almost...  that this is
a prop knife.
And I'm ashamed, actually, that I'm not
really dead.
But I'm also flattered that they really
bought my death.
I stand here, ashamed and flattered,
despite my audience having disappeared
into the forest.
Now I feel disgusted standing here,
ashamed and flattered.
On the other hand, I feel a certain
satisfaction of being disgusted about
being ashamed and flattered.
All the same, it's proud-spirited being
satisfied of being disgusted about
being ashamed and flattered.
But if I'm going to start pondering
being proud, that'll give me a headache.
And it seems rather stupid to stand here
in the middle of a dark forest all alone
with a headache
because of my satisfaction with being
disgusted about being ashamed
and flattered.
I've come to fetch you.
To a strict and black lord.
He says that he needs your lute.
You're going to play at a dance tonight
down by the border stone.
I don't have the time.
My strict lord thought you were going to
respond that way.
- He says that you lie.
- I've got a performance.
It's cancelled.
- My contract.
- Your contract is cancelled.
My children...  my family...
They'll manage a lot better without you.
- Is there no subterfuge?
- No.
No loopholes?
- No exceptions?
- No.
There are no loopholes.
Sounds like a strict master.
It is a strict master.
Let's go then and find him, before he
gets pissed off.
- Why are you sighing?
- I'm just sighing!  Is that against
the law?
The wanderers are very tired.
They've reached a glade in the forest,
and there they sink down into the moss.
They lie there silently, listening to
their breaths
their pulses, the wind in the tree tops.
Maria is a bit outside the group with
her child.
She looks at the moonlight which is no
longer silent and dead.
It's secretive and shifting.
One morning, the holy virgin went to the
well to get water.
The lizards scurried across the stones,
and one was in the light and one was in
the shade.
She leaned against the well and
peered down into the dark water.
Her cheeks had gotten thinner.
And her eyes had grown bigger.
It felt heavy carrying the child just
that morning in the white heat of
the sun.
So she cried a bit, and he tears dropped
down into the well's water.
And when she'd finished crying
and that didn't take long
she felt a bit better, almost happy
and she took some water in her cup.
The sun sparkled in the tall pines
and the light splashed all over her red
dress and her naked feet.
She wiped her tears, salt stinging
her cheeks.
She drank from the fresh water.
She drank from her hands that she formed
into a cup.
Then...
The child moved in her womb.
And she laughed loudly in
her loneliness.
She straightened her back, with
arms akimbo.
She raised the water vessel in her
brown, sinewy arms.
The she walked the few steps up to the
carpenter's house
She walked through the sweltering heat
of the morning
but her steps were almost like a dance.
From the roads you could hear the
barking of the sheepdogs and the shouts
from the shepherds.
They were driving their herds to
the mountains
to the olive groves' refreshing shadow.
This was my song about the virgin Mary.
We have reached the starting point.
By the border stone.
You have walked in a circle and now
you're sitting, waiting and freezing in
the dawn.
The wind is increasing and the clouds
are amassing at the horizon which is
greying in the dawn.
Who is the woman standing over there?
The wife of the knight Antonius Block.
I left the farm because of the plague.
I was one of the last ones.
What are you doing here?
Do you see the fires over there?
Do you hear the music?
It's the other country's soldiers who
have blocked the border with a tall
fence that crosses the entire country
from coast to coast.
There's soldiers everywhere.
Nobody from the plague-stricken country
are allowed entrance.
We just have to wait.
What are we waiting for?
For nothing.
For the plague.
Poor Atonius Block.
Poor dear; do you recognise me?
I can see that it's you now.
Somewhere in your eyes, somewhere in
your face
but hidden away, but scared, is that boy
who left all those years ago.
Was is a good and amusing crusade?
Did you manage to kill a lot
of heathens?
Did you ride really fast and smash a lot
of swords and lances?
Did you pray a lot of prayers at the
holy grave?
Did you rape a lot of women?
Are you cold?
Do you want to borrow my shawl?
No?
In the ocean fishes swim
Big ships are rocked
Silence!
Don't you hear that?
What are we supposed to hear?
Now the roosters in the other country
are crowing where the dawn is meeting
the plain.
Now the fires are going out.
Now the wind is calming down.
Now the rain is starting to fall, silent
and mild.
Now we're standing here, tightly
together, waiting for somebody that's
coming towards us from over there.
It's a powerful man.
A knight.
A gentleman.
And he's got a young girl in his
entourage.
And a jester with his lute on his back.
There's coming here.
They're coming here, to us, through
the silent dawn rain.
Good morning, my high lord.
We're standing here, together, waiting
for you.
My name is Jens.
A Jens person.
Who talks a lot during an
endless stroll.
There's a scrawny and miserable knight.
With a whole lot of confused and
feverish thoughts under his hat.
I'm the knight's wife.
There's a little witch, who, from what
I've heard
is supposed to have pleasured herself
with the dark one.
She was burned for her faith.
By now she's probably
pretty disappointed.
I'm a smith by profession.
And pretty good.
This is my wife, Lisa.
Curtsy for the lord, Lisa.
She's hard to handle, sometimes.
We've had some hullabaloo, so to say.
A bit more than most people.
It was the jester's fault.
Ask him yourself; he's standing
right there.
Over there's a woman who calls
herself Maria.
She's been running days and nights
to escape.
Perhaps not so much for her own sake, as
for the child's.
Now she stands there, quiet, and waits.
I can tell you what the knight is
shouting, even if his tongue has been
stolen from him
and only strange sounds escape him.
Every morning he stretches his arms
towards the saints, towards god.
Often he shouts in their holy ears for
them to hear him.
Time and time again, he's shook by
certainty.
Through fogs of spiritual lethargy he's
struck by god's presence
like a blow from a huge bell.
Suddenly his emptiness is filled with
a music
without notes, but carried as if
by voices
Then he shouts through all his
darknesses, and his shout is like
a whisper.
To your presence, o god.
For your honour, I live.
For your honour.
That's what he's shouting in
the darkness.
Then the terrible thing happens: His
certainty goes out, as if somebody blew
out a candle.
The huge bell falls silent.
The darkness pulses even darker.
It forces itself through his throat and
presses against his mouth.
The curses appear through his stomach,
his hair, his eyes.
Like a predator
like shine small snakes
like evil little birds with
hoarse screams
Then his darkness is spotted by blood
Then his wounds expand.
With all respect for the strict lord, I
ask you to stop making those sounds.
Out there in the darkness, that you
claim to visit
where presumably we all visit like
stupid little heavenly bodies
in that darkness you won't find anybody
to care about your complaints or
your suffering.
So dry your tears and reflect in
your indifference.
From me you could have gotten a herb.
To laxatively purge your problems
with eternity.
It seems to be too late now.
Feel, at least, in these final minutes,
the incommensurate triumph
to be able to roll your eyes and move
your toes.
Be silent.
I'll be quiet.
But under protest.
I got a bit embarrassed, I admit that.
But should I just give up without free
will and resistance?
With all due respect for the
strict lord.
Quiet.
The jester is tuning his lute.
The strict lord is inviting us to dance.
He wants us to hold hands.
And then thread the dance in a long row.
First the strict lord.
The musician brings up the rear.
Away from the dawn we're going.
Away towards the dark country
while the rain is washing down
our faces.
Come to the dance, my children,
my friends.
The strict lord is impatient.
And the music has just...